In the PCA algorithm we take
PCAのアルゴリズムにおいては、
N dimensional features and reduce
n次元のフィーチャーを引数に取り
them to some K dimensional feature representation.
それをある数kの次元のフィーチャーの表現へと縮小する。
This number K is a parameter
この数kがPCAアルゴリズムの
of the PCA algorithm.
パラメータとなる。
This number K is also called
この数字kはまた、
the number of principle components
主成分の数、あるいは保持する主成分の総数
or the number of principle components that we've retained.
とも呼ばれる物だ。
And in this video I'd like
そしてこのビデオで、
to give you some guidelines,
PCAのパラメータkを選ぶのに
tell you about how people
人々がどんなやり方で
tend to think about how to
選ぶ事が多いのかの
choose this parameter K for PCA.
ガイドラインを与えたい。
In order to choose k,
kを選ぶ為に、
that is to choose the number
それは主成分の数を選ぶという事だが、
of principal components, here are a couple of useful concepts.
その為に有用な幾つかのコンセプトをここに示す。
What PCA tries to do
PCAがやろうとする事は、
is it tries to minimize
二乗射影誤差の平均を
the average squared projection error.
最小化しようとする事だ。
So it tries to minimize
つまりPCAは、
this quantity, which I'm writing down,
この量を最小化しようと試みる。ここに書きだした奴。
which is the difference between the
これは元のデータxと
original data X and the
射影したバージョンx-approx-iとの
projected version, X-approx-i, which
差分で、
was defined last video, so
これは前回のビデオで定義した物だ。
it tries to minimize the squared
PCAはxとそれをより次元の低い表面へと
distance between x and it's projection
射影した点との距離の二乗を
onto that lower dimensional surface.
最小化しようとする。
So that's the average square projection error.
これが二乗射影誤差の平均だ。
Also let me define the
そしてまた、データ全体の
total variation in the
分散も定義しておこう。
data to be the
それは
average length squared of
これらの手本xiの
these examples Xi
長さの二乗の平均だ。
so the total variation in the
つまりデータ全体の分散は、
data is the average of
トレーニングセット内の
my training sets of the
各トレーニング手本の長さの
length of each of my training examples.
平均だ。
And this one says, "On average, how
そしてこれの意味する所は、
far are my training examples
「平均では、我らの手本は
from the vector, from just being all zeros?"
全てがゼロのベクトルから、どれだけ離れているか？
How far is, how far
平均では我らのトレーニング手本は
on average are my training examples from the origin?
原点からどれだけ離れているだろうか？」
When we're trying to choose k, a
我らがkを選ぼうとする時には、
pretty common rule of thumb
kを選ぶのに良く使われる
for choosing k is to choose
経験則としては、
the smaller values so that
これらの値の比が、
the ratio between these is less than 0.01.
0.01未満となるように選ぶ、という物がある。
So in other words,
言い換えると、
a pretty common way to
我らがkを選ぶ
think about how we choose k
とても良くやるやり方は、
is we want the average squared projection error.
二乗射影誤差の平均を求める、という事。
That is the average distance
それはxと射影との
between x and it's projections
距離の平均を、
divided by the total variation of the data.
データ全体の分散で割った物。
That is how much the data varies.
この全体の分散は、データがどれほど変化するかを表す。
We want this ratio to be
我らはこの比率を、
less than, let's say, 0.01.
例えば0.01未満にしたい、とする。
Or to be less than 1%, which is another way of thinking about it.
言い換えると1%未満、と考えても良い。
And the way most people think
そしてほとんどの人々が
about choosing K is rather
kを選ぶという事を考える時には、
than choosing K directly the
kを直接選ぶのではなく、
way most people talk about
多くの人の考え方としては、
it is as what this
この値が幾つか、
number is, whether it is 0.01
という事。これが0.01だろうか？
or some other number.
または別の数だろうか？
And if it is 0.01, another way
そしてもしこれが0.01なら、
to say this to use the
PCAの用語を用いてこれを
language of PCA is that 99% of the variance is retained.
違う言い方で言うと、99%の分散が保持されている、と言う。
I don't really want to, don't
私は本当に、、、
worry about what this phrase
技術的にこのフレーズが一体何を意味しているのかについて、
really means technically but this
そんなに気にしないで欲しい。
phrase "99% of variance is retained" just means
このフレーズ、「99%の分散が保持されている」というのは、単に
that this quantity on the left is less than 0.01.
この左側の量が0.01未満だと言っているに過ぎない。
And so, if you
だから、もしあなたが
are using PCA and if you want
PCAを使っていて、そして他の人に、
to tell someone, you know,
どれだけの数の主成分を
how many principle components you've
残したのか、について伝えたい時は、
retained it would be
私は、kを
more common to say well, I
99%の分散が保持されるように選んだ、
chose k so that 99% of the variance was retained.
と言う方が、より一般的だ。
And that's kind of a useful thing
そしてそれは、知っておくと役に立つ事だ。
to know, it means that you
それの意味する所は、
know, the average squared projection
平均の二乗射影誤差を
error divided by the total
全体の分散で割ると、
variation that was at most 1%.
それがたかだが1%だという事だ。
That's kind of an insightful
それは考えてみるになかなか
thing to think about, whereas if
洞察に富んだ事だ。
you tell someone that, "Well I
一方でもしあなたが誰かに
had to 100 principle
「100個の主成分を得た」とか、
components" or "k was equal
「kはイコール100で、
to 100 in a thousand dimensional
元の次元は1000次元のデータだった」
data" it's a little
とか言っても、
hard for people to interpret
これを聞いた人にとっては
that.
解釈が難しい。
So this number 0.01 is what people often use.
そこでこの数字、0.01というのを人々は良く使う。
Other common values is 0.05,
その他良く使われるのは0.05。
and so this would be 5%,
こちらは5%。
and if you do that then
もしこちらを用いると
you go and say well 95%
人の所に行って、こう言う事が出来る：
of the variance is
分散の95%は
retained and, you know
保持されています、と。
other numbers maybe 90% of the variance is
他の数字としては、分散の90%が保持されている、とか、
retained, maybe as low as 85%.
85%くらいまではありうるかもしれない。
So 90% would correspond to say
90%は0.10に対応した物で、
0.10, kinda 10%.
つまり10%。
And so range of values
つまり、値の範囲として、
from, you know, 90, 95,
90, 95, 99, そして低くても85%くらいまでの中に
99, maybe as low as 85% of
含まれる値は、
the variables contained would be a fairly typical range in values.
値としてはかなり典型的な範囲だろう。
Maybe 95 to 99
95から99の値が
is really the most
人々が用いる値としては
common range of values that people use.
もっとも一般的な範囲だと思う。
For many data sets you'd be
多くのデータセットにおいて、
surprised, in order to retain
99%の分散を保持するのに、
99% of the variance, you can
凄いデータの次元を削減出来て、
often reduce the dimension of
しかもほとんどの分散を保持したままに出来る事に
the data significantly and still retain most of the variance.
しばしば驚く事になろう。
Because for most real life
何故なら多くの現実世界のデータは、
data says many features are
多くのフィーチャーがお互いに
just highly correlated, and so
高い相関を持っているから。
it turns out to be possible
だからデータを
to compress the data a
大量に圧縮しつつ、
lot and still retain you
多くの分散、例えば
know 99% of the variance
99%とか95%の分散を保持する事も
or 95% of the variance. So how do you implement this?
可能となる。 ではこれをどう実装したらいいだろう？
Well, here's one algorithm that you might use.
これが一つ、使えそうなアルゴリズムだ。
You may start off, if you
もしあなたがkの値を
want to choose the value of
選びたいとすると、
k, we might start off with k equals 1.
k=1から始める。
And then we run through PCA.
そしてPCAを実行する。
You know, so we compute, you
つまりUreduceを計算して、
reduce, compute z1, z2, up to zm.
z(1), z(2), ... , z(m)と計算して、
Compute all of those x1
x1 approx, ...とxm approxまでを
approx and so on up to xm approx
全て計算する。
and then we check if 99% of the variance is retained.
そして分散が99%保持されているかどうかをチェックする。
Then we're good and we use k equals 1.
そしてもし保持されていれば、k=1を使う。
But if it isn't then what we'll do we'll next try K equals 2.
保持されていなければ、次に進み、k=2を試す。
And then we'll again
そしてまたこの手続き全体を
run through this entire procedure and
繰り返して、そして
check, you know is this expression satisfied.
この式が満たされているかをチェックする、
Is this less than 0.01. And if not then we do this again.
これは0.01未満だろうか。そして満たしていなかったら、またこれを繰り返す。
Let's try k equals 3,
k=3を試そう、
then try k equals 4,
次にk=4を試そう、
and so on until maybe
そうやって、例えば
we get up to k equals
k=17まで行った所で、
17 and we find 99% of
99%のデータが保持されている、という事を
the data have is retained and then
見出したとする。
we use k equals 17, right?
その場合はk=17とする訳だ。
That is one way
これはkの
to choose the smallest value
99%の分散を保持する最小の値を探す
of k, so that and 99% of the variance is retained.
方法の一つだ。
But as you can imagine,
だが想像出来るように、
this procedure seems horribly inefficient
この手続は恐ろしいほど効率が悪い。
we're trying k equals one, k equals two, we're doing all these calculations.
我らはk=1を試し、k=2、とこれらの計算をやり続ける。
Fortunately when you implement
幸運な事に、PCAを実装する時には、
PCA it actually, in
この手順の所で、
this step, it actually gives us
実際にはこれらの事を
a quantity that makes it
同じように計算する、もっと簡単な方法を可能にする
much easier to compute these things as well.
量を与えてくれる。
Specifically when you're calling
具体的には、これらの行列、
SVD to get these
U, S, Vを取る為に
matrices u, s, and d,
svdを呼んだら、
when you're calling usvd on the
共分散行列 Sigmaに対して
covariance matrix sigma, it also
svdをコールしたら、
gives us back this matrix
それはSという行列も返す。
S and what
このSが何かというと、
S is, is going to
SはN掛けるNの
be a square matrix an N by N matrix in fact,
正方行列であり、
that is
実際は、
diagonal.
対角行列でもある。
So is diagonal entries s one
そして対角成分であるs11,
one, s two two, s
s22,
three three down to s
s33、、、とsnnまであるが、
n n are going to
それらだけが
be the only non-zero elements of
この行列の中の非ゼロ成分で、
this matrix, and everything off
対角成分から外れた全ての成分は
the diagonals is going to be zero.
0となる。
Okay?
分かりましたか。
So those big O's that I'm drawing,
ここに描いたこれらの大きなOは、
by that what I mean is
これの意味する所は、
that everything off the diagonal
この行列の
of this matrix all of those
対角成分から外れた成分は
entries there are going to be zeros.
全てゼロとなる、という事だ。
And so, what is possible
そして証明出来る事として、
to show, and I won't prove
ここでその証明をして見るつもりは無いが、
this here, and it turns out
ある所与の値kに対し、
that for a given value of
ここにある値は、
k, this quantity
もっとシンプルに計算出来る、
over here can be computed much more simply.
という事が、知られている。
And that quantity can be computed
そしてその値は、
as one minus sum from
1引くことの i=1からkまでの
i equals 1 through
和をとる事のsii、
K of Sii divided by
割ることの
sum from I equals 1
和を取る事のi=1からnまでの
through N of Sii.
sii。
So just to say that it words, or
これを言葉で説明すると、
just to take another
あるいはこれを説明する為に
view of how to explain that,
別の見方で見てみると、
if K equals 3 let's say.
例えばk=3だとすると、
What we're going to do to
分子を計算する為に
compute the numerator is sum
我らがやる事は、
from one--  I equals 1
和を取る事のi=1から3までの
through 3 of of Sii, so just
siiを計算する、
compute the sum of these first three elements.
つまり、単にこの最初の三つの要素の和を計算する。
So that's the numerator.
これが分子となる。
And then for the denominator, well that's
そして分母は、
the sum of all of these diagonal entries.
この対角成分全ての和だ。
And one minus the ratio of
そして1から引くことのその比、
that, that gives me this
それがここの量を
quantity over here, that I've
与えるのだ。
circled in blue.
この青で丸く囲んだこれ。
And so, what we can do
そこで我らは、
is just test if this
たんにこれが0.01以上かどうかを
is less than or equal to 0.01.
テストする事が出来る。
Or equivalently, we can test
または同じ事だが、
if the sum from
i=1からkまでのsiiの和を
i equals 1 through k, s-i-i
割ることの i=1からnまでのsiiの和
divided by sum from i
これが0.99以上かどうかを
equals 1 through n, s-i-i
テストしても
if this is greater than or
構わない。
equal to 4.99, if you
もしあなたが分散の99%を
want to be sure that 99% of the variance is retained.
保持したいと思うのなら。
And so what you can do
そこであなたが出来る事としては、
is just slowly increase k,
単純にちょっとずつkを増加させていって、
set k equals one, set k equals
k=1をセットし、k=2をセットし、
two, set k equals three and so
k=3をセットし、、、と続けていって、
on, and just test this quantity
そしてこの量をテストしていって、
to see what is the
99%の分散を保持する事を保証する中で、
smallest value of k that ensures that 99% of the variance is retained.
最小となるkの値を見てみる。
And if you do
もしこれをやれば、
this, then you need to call
svd関数はたったの一回
the SVD function only once.
呼ぶだけで良い。
Because that gives you the
何故ならそれでS行列が得られるから。
S matrix and once you
ひとたびS行列を
have the S matrix, you can
得てしまえば、
then just keep on doing
あなたはこの計算を
this calculation by increasing
分子のkの値を増やしていくだけで
the value of K in the
計算していく事が出来て、
numerator and so you
だからsvdを
don't need keep to calling SVD over
異なる値のkを試す都度何度も何度も
and over again to test out the different values of K.
呼びつづける必要は無い。
So this procedure is much more
つまりこの手続きは、
efficient, and this can
もっとずっと効率的だ。
allow you to select the
そしてこの方法により、
value of K without needing
PCAを最初から、何度も何度も
to run PCA from scratch
走らせる必要無く、
over and over. You just run SVD once, this
kの値を選ぶ事が出来る。単にsvdを一回走らせるだけで、
gives you all of these diagonal numbers,
これらの対角成分の値を与えてくれる、
all of these numbers S11, S22 down to SNN,
これらの値全て、s11、s22とsnnまでの値全て。
and then you can
そしてそこで、単に
just you know, vary K
この式の
in this expression to find
kを変えていくだけで、
the smallest value of K, so
99%の分散が保持される最小のkを
that 99% of the variance is retained.
見つける事が出来る。
So to summarize, the way
ではまとめよう。
that I often use, the
PCAを圧縮の目的で
way that I often choose K
使う時に、
when I am using PCA for compression
私がkを選ぶ為に良くやるのは、
is I would call SVD once
svdを共分散行列に対して
in the covariance matrix, and then
一回実行して、
I would use this formula and
そしてこの式を使って、
pick the smallest value of
この式を満たす最小のkを
K for which this expression is satisfied.
選び出す。
And by the way, even if you
ところで、
were to pick some different value
たとえあなたが違うkの値を選んだとしても、
of K, even if you were
たとえあなたがkの値を
to pick the value of K
手動で選んで、
manually, you know maybe you
例えば1000次元のデータに対して
have a thousand dimensional data
k=100を
and I just want to choose K equals one hundred.
選びたい、としよう。
Then, if you want to explain
その場合でも、あなたがやった事を
to others what you just did,
他の人に説明したいと思ったら、
a good way to explain the performance
あなたのPCAの実装のパフォーマンスを
of your implementation of PCA to
他の人に伝える良い方法としては、
them, is actually to take
実際にこの量を
this quantity and compute what
計算してみる事だ。
this is, and that will
この値はあなたに、
tell you what was the percentage of variance retained.
分散の何％が保持されているかを教えてくれる。
And if you report that number, then,
そしてあなたがこの数字を報告すれば、
you know, people that are familiar
PCAに慣れている人たちなら、
with PCA, and people can
そういう人たちなら
use this to get a
これを用いる事で、
good understanding of how well
あなたの100次元の表現が、
your hundred dimensional representation is
元のデータセットをどれくらい良く近似出来ているかを
approximating your original data
良く理解する事が出来る。
set, because there's 99% of variance retained.
何故なら99%の分散が保持されているのだから、
That's really a measure of your
それは実際にあなたの
square of construction error, that
施工誤差の二乗を測る指標だ。
ratio being 0.01, just
その比が0.01というなら、
gives people a good intuitive
人々にあなたのPCAの実装が
sense of whether your implementation
オリジナルのデータセットの良い近似を
of PCA is finding a
発見したかについての
good approximation of your original data set.
良い理解を与える。
So hopefully, that gives you
以上で、数字のkを選ぶ
an efficient procedure for choosing
効率的な手続きを
the number K. For choosing
提供出来ただろうか。このkを選ぶ事で、
what dimension to reduce your
データを何次元まで削減するかを
data to, and if
選ぶ事になる。
you apply PCA to very
そしてもしあなたがPCAを
high dimensional data sets, you know, to like
とても高い次元のデータセットに適用するなら、
a thousand dimensional data, very often,
1000次元のデータとか、
just because data sets tend
とてもよく、データセットが
to have highly correlated
高い相関を持つフィーチャーを含むので、
features, this is just a
これは単に、多くのデータにおいて
property of most of the data sets you see,
あなたが目にする事になる性質なので、
you often find that PCA
あなたは良く、PCAが
will be able to retain ninety nine
分散の99%を保持していながら、とか、
per cent of the variance or say,
あるいは95とか99とか、
ninety five ninety nine, some
とにかく高い割合の分散を
high fraction of the variance,
保持していながら、
even while compressing the data
とても多くの割合のデータを
by a very large factor.
圧縮する事が出来る、という状況を目にする事になるだろう。